<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short ansvver of Iohn Ling to the 16. quæres of Ioseph Heming, about Christmas. Wherein all the care that can be is taken to avoyd expence of paper, so much having beene spoyled already ...</title>
            <author>Ling, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88305</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2335A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R179758</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504491</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504491</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171808</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88305)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171808)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2592:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short ansvver of Iohn Ling to the 16. quæres of Ioseph Heming, about Christmas. Wherein all the care that can be is taken to avoyd expence of paper, so much having beene spoyled already ...</title>
                  <author>Ling, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Sutro Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Heming, Joseph. --  Certain quæries touching the rise and observation of Christmas.</term>
               <term>Christmas --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171808:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
            <p>A ſhort ANSVVER OF <hi>IOHN LING,</hi> To the 16. Quaeres of <hi>Ioſeph Heming,</hi> about CHRISTMAS.</p>
            <p>Wherein all the care that can be is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to avoyd expence of paper, ſo much ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beene ſpoyled already. For</p>
            <q>
               <l>Wer't not for Chriſtmas which is nigh,</l>
               <l>When fruit, ſpice, eaten and digeſted Pie</l>
               <l>Calls for more paper, no man could make ſhift</l>
               <l>How to employ <hi>JOS. HEMING</hi> to his thrift.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171808:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171808:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
            <head>A ſhort Anſwer of <hi>Iohn Ling</hi> to the <hi>16.</hi> Quaeres of <hi>Ioſeph Heming</hi> about Chriſtmas.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is perceived that one <hi>Joſeph Heming,</hi> not long before Chriſtmas, 1648. (as by his printed Paper doth appeare) from his Study in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ttoxeter,</hi> otherwiſe and vulgarly <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>x<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> in the ſayd yeare doth challenge all thoſe who can write and reade, to anſwer his 16. Quaeries concerning the obſervation of the Feaſt of Chriſtmas, or the Nativity of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; to which I <hi>John Ling</hi> having been a Grammer Schollar, and having ſeene ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in the world both in this Church, and the Reformed beyond Sea, doe make this Anſwer.</p>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The firſt Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether ſuch religious cuſtomes as are binding to all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Ieſus Chriſt, ought not to have ſure footing upon the Word of God, or Apoſtolicall practice?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Resp.</label> Becauſe I will not make Paper deare by long Anſwers or Recitalls, I ſay ſuch Religious Cuſtomes as are binding to all the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, ought to have footing upon the word of God, or Apoſtolicall practice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The ſecond Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether you can ſubſtantially prove that Chriſt was borne on the</hi> 25 <hi>of</hi> December? <hi>And what your proofes are?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171808:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->
               <p>
                  <label>Resp.</label> It is not materiall, I, or no, whether I can prove that Chriſt was borne on the 25 of <hi>December,</hi> as it now ſtandeth in the Engliſh Calendar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The third Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether the celebration of that day (grant he was borne on it) can be clearely warranted by you from Scripture? And what your Scriptures are?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Resp.</label> It imports no more then what is anſwered in the firſt and ſecond.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The fourth Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether you can cleare it by ſound conſequence from the New Teſtament, though not ſet downe there</hi> in totidem verbis?</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Resp.</label> It is cleared by ſound conſequence, both from the Old and New Teſtament, that the day of the Birth of our Saviour, God and man, ſhould be kept with Feſtivity: I will now firſt give you inſtance in the Angels ſong to the Shepheards, <hi>Glory be to God on high, on earth peace, good will towards men,</hi> ſee the 118 Pſalme, 22.23. and 24. verſes, <hi>The ſtone which the builders refuſed is the head of the corner,</hi> which is interpreted in the New Teſtament to be meant of Chriſt. 24. <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made, wee will rejoyce and be glad in it,</hi> which all good Interpreters ſay to be meant by the day of the Birth of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. Many places there are in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and other of the Prophets: So that now you have better proofes from Scripture for keeping holy an Anniverſary day for the celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Birth of our Lord, then for changing the Sabbath to the Lords day; the proofes whereof are chiefely grounded upon Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Cuſtome, <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 28.16. <hi>Math.</hi> 21.42. <hi>Acts,</hi> 4.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.33. 1. <hi>Peter,</hi> 2.6. and 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The fifth Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether you can doe it by univerſall tradition?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:171808:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->
               <p>
                  <label>Resp.</label> Its done by Univerſall Tradition, and in that I will bring it to the Cuſtomary Practice of the Reformed Churches of Dutch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> French, and Geneva.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The ſixt Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether (in caſe it can be evidenced by none of theſe,</hi> viz. <hi>plaine Text, ſollid Inference, univerſall Tradition) it be not a meere humane invention, and ſo Will worſhip? And how you will one day acquit your ſelves before God, for placing, and crying up mens Inventions, inſtead of the inſtitutions of Ieſus Chriſt? And whether it were not faithfull dealing with poore ſimple people to tell them that you have neither of theſe to warrant it?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> I anſwer, it were falſe dealing to tell Chriſtian People that which were untrue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The ſeaventh Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>(Since dayes and times commanded by God himſelfe to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved under the Law, were, and are unlawfull under the Goſpel) Whether dayes and times commanded by men, and not by God, under the Goſpell, are not leſſe lawfull?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> If this day and time were onely commanded by men, it were unlawfull, ſo far as to command it as a meere Religious duty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The eighth Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether the true and genuine Interpretation of</hi> Chriſtmas <hi>be</hi> Chriſt man? <hi>And whether to perſwade people 'tis ſo, be not to abuſe and delude them? And whether we may not as well inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret</hi> Candlemas Candleman, Michaelmas Michaelman, <hi>as</hi> Chriſtmas Chriſtman?</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> (Becauſe you make ſport, and have brought in a Gamboll)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171808:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->That I have a conjecture that <hi>Joſeph Heming</hi> is ſome Schoole Maſter, or ſome great Schoole Boy, that can interpret the Latine <hi>Mas</hi> for a man, and then Chriſtmas is Chriſtman; and certainely it is to abuſe people to perſwade them ſo and ſo of the reſt: But I have heard what was anſwered Dr. <hi>Lambe</hi> by a good fellow, to whom he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to have ſayd Chriſtyde, and why not as well <hi>Tom</hi> tyde? The Anſwer was he could ſay <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> or <hi>Thomas,</hi> or <hi>Lambe,</hi> aſſe, and ſo he left him, and ſo doe I you with your Gamboll.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The ninth Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether the Saints are bound to rejoyce in the Birth of Chriſt on that day men ſuperſtitiouſly call</hi> Chriſtmas, <hi>more then at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times? And whether the Lords day be not [the] day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted for them to rejoyce on?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> You begge the Queſtion of Superſtition, and ſo untill you frame the Argument out of the Queſtion in Moode and Figure, I ſhall anſwer you no more upon that poynt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The tenth Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether</hi> Chriſtmas <hi>day ought in any reſpect to be eſteemed above another of the Weeke dayes? And whether people may not without offence to God follow their lawfull vocations on that day?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> That by the eſtabliſhed Lawes of this Kingdome, in the times of the firſt Reformation (and ſtill continued) this is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be kept as a holy day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The eleaventh Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether you thinke the Parliament and Aſſembly have erred and played the fooles in condemning and raſing out Holy dayes not warranted in the Word? And whether to obſerve them, be not highly to diſlike, and flatly to contradict (in poynt of practice at leaſt) their proceedings in order to a Reformation?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:171808:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->
               <p>
                  <label>Resp.</label> I ſay it is a Propoſition of ill language, and therefore I ſay no more, but demand of you whether you thinke the firſt Reformers that ſuffered Martyrdome were Fooles and Knaves?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The twelfth Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether (ſince moſt men and women in</hi> England <hi>doe blindely and ſuperstitiouſly beleeve Chriſt was borne that day) preaching on it, doth not nouriſh and ſtrengthen them in that beliefe?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> At firſt you begge the Queſtion, but to the ſecond part of it; I ſay ſince preaching is lawfull upon any day; ſo is it expedient, if not neceſſary upon a day commanded.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The thirteenth Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether this</hi> Feaſt <hi>had not its riſe and growth from Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans conformity to the mad Feaſts</hi> Saturnalia (<hi>kept in</hi> December <hi>to</hi> Saturne <hi>the Father of Gods</hi>) <hi>in which there was a Sheafe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to</hi> Ceres <hi>Goddeſſe of Corne, a hymne in her praiſe called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>? And whether thoſe Chriſtians by name, to cloake it, did not afterwards call it</hi> Yule; <hi>and</hi> Chriſtmas <hi>(as though it were for Chriſts honour?) And whether it be not yet by ſome (more ancient then truely or knowingly religious) called</hi> Yule, <hi>and the mad playes (wherewith 'tis celebrated like thoſe</hi> Saturna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia) Yule <hi>games? And whether from the offering of that Sheafe to</hi> Ceres; <hi>from that ſong in her praiſe: from thoſe gifts the Heathens gave their friends in the Calends of</hi> January, ominis gratia; <hi>did not ariſe or ſpring our blazes;</hi> Chriſtmas <hi>Kariles, and</hi> New yeares <hi>gifts?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Resp.</label> Whether this Feaſt had not its Rice from Chriſtians confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the mad Feaſt <hi>Saturnalia,</hi> I anſwer, I thinke it a very mad Queſtion: But I confeſſe in ſome Nations they call that Feaſt <hi>Yule,</hi> and amongſt your brethren the Scots, they call it <hi>Zule,</hi> as I have found it in their Callenders; but untill you can prove that thoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171808:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 27 -->ſpeake Greeke, you will be far to ſeeke for your Argument: Therefore good Mr. Schoolemaſter, or Schooleboy, leave off your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymologies; for you will finde it hard to prove that Chriſtians uſed to celebrate this Feaſt in any relation to the <hi>Saturnalia</hi> or <hi>Ceres</hi> Songs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The fourteenth Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether conformity to, and retention of Heatheniſh Cuſtomes be commendable in Chriſtians, ſutable or agreeable with Goſpel Principles, though under pretext of Chriſts Honour and Worſhip?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Resp.</label> In the Negative it is not lawfull; but how will you apply it, <hi>John Ellis,</hi> I cry you mercy <hi>Joſeph Heming?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The fifteenth Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether you are not bound to prove your practice for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction and ſatisfaction of your Brethren, whoſe duty it is to walke with you in things agreeable to the minde of Chriſt? And in caſe you cannot; Whether you ought not to acknowledge your errour, lay downe your practice (as others have done theirs) no longer befooling and miſleading the people committed to your charge?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, this reproofe would ſerve for a Preacher if he had miſled his people, of which number I am not, but if this charge be unjuſt, ſee how you diſobey the Lawes of God and man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>The ſixteenth Quaere.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether in caſe you returne no Anſwer to theſe Quaeries, I have not ground ſufficient to conclude you utterly unable to give any rationall account of your practice, now put upon it?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Resp.</label> Whether I have anſwered your Quaeries or no; Let me know it by your confeſſion or Reply.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From no great Study,</hi> 
                     <date>this 23 <hi>of Dec.</hi> 1648.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
